<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The picture of the Councell of State, held forth to the free people of England by Lieut. Col. John Lilburn, M. Thomas Prince, and M. Richard Overton, now prisoners in the Tower of London for bearing testimony to the liberties of England against the present tyrants at White-Hall, and their associates, or, a full narrative of the late extrajudiciall and military proceedings against them ; together with the substance of their severall examinations, answers, and deportments before them at Darby-house, upon March 28 last.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13113940</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13113940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 744:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The picture of the Councell of State, held forth to the free people of England by Lieut. Col. John Lilburn, M. Thomas Prince, and M. Richard Overton, now prisoners in the Tower of London for bearing testimony to the liberties of England against the present tyrants at White-Hall, and their associates, or, a full narrative of the late extrajudiciall and military proceedings against them ; together with the substance of their severall examinations, answers, and deportments before them at Darby-house, upon March 28 last.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Prince, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with many large additions by the authours themselves.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PICTURE <hi>OF THE</hi> Councell of State, <hi>Held forth to the</hi> Free People of England BY Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Prince,</hi> and M. <hi>Richard Overton,</hi> now priſoners in the Tower of LONDON, For bearing teſtimony to the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> againſt the preſent Tyrants at WHITE-HALL, and their Aſſociates.</p>
            <p>OR, A full NARRATIVE of the late extrajudiciall and Military Proceedings againſt them.</p>
            <p>Together with the Subſtance of their ſeverall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations, Anſwers, and Deportments before them at <hi>Darby-</hi>houſe, upon <hi>March</hi> 28 laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Edition, with many large Additions by the Authours themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeer, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97720:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97720:2"/>
            <head>THE PICTURE OF THE Councel of State: <hi>Held forth to the Free People of England, by Lieut. Col.</hi> John Lilburn, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Prince, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Richard Overton.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Narrative of the Proceedings againſt Lieutenant Col. <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> thus followeth.</head>
               <p>ON <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 28 of <hi>March</hi> 1649, about four or five a clock in the morning, my lodging at <hi>Wincheſter-houſe</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> was beſet with about 100 or 200 armed men, Horſe and Foot, one of which knocking at my Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, I roſe and opened him the door, and asked him who he would ſpeak with, and what he would have? He replyed, he was come to take me priſoner; whereupon I demanded of him to ſee his Warrant; he told me he had one, but had it not here, but as ſoon as I came to <hi>Pauls</hi> I ſhould ſee it; I told him, if he walked by the rules of juſtice, he ought to have brought his Warrant with him, and to have ſhewed it me, and given me leave to have copied it out, if I had deſired it. But divers of the foot Souldiers ruſhing into my room at his heels; I deſired him to demean himſelf like a Gentleman, and not with any incivilities affright my children and family; for if it were nothing but my perſon he would have, I would but make me ready, and go along with him without any more ado, whither he would carry me; for his power of armed men was beyond my preſent reſiſting, or power to diſpute: ſo I deſired him and another Gentleman with him to ſit down, which they did; and when I was almoſt ready to go, I demanded of him whether it would not fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his end, in my going along with him and one or two more of his company in a boat, and I would ingage unto him as I was an Engliſh man, there ſhould be no diſturbance to him by me, or any in my behalf, but I would quietly and peacebly go with him where-ever he would have me: but he told me no, I muſt march thorow the ſtreets with the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97720:3"/>
Guard that came for me: I told him, I could not now diſpute, but it would be no great conqueſt to lead a ſingle captive thorow the ſtreets in the head of ſo many armed men, who neither had made reſiſtance, nor was in any capacity to do it; and coming down ſtairs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great yard, I was commanded to ſtand till the men were marſhalled in Rank and File, and two other priſoners were brought unto me, <hi>viz. my Landlord</hi> Mr. <hi>Devenniſh's two Sons,</hi> but for what they knew not, nor could imagine; So away thorow the ſtreets the armed Victors carry us, like three conquered Slaves, making us often halt by the way, that ſo their men might draw up in good order, to encounter with an Army of Butterflies, in caſe they ſhould meet them in the way to reſcue us their Captives from them; ſo coming to <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, I there meet with my Comrade M. <hi>Prince,</hi> and after imbraces each of other, and a little diſcourſe, we ſee our acquaintance M. <hi>William Walwin</hi> marching at the head of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Party as a captive; and having underſtood that our being ſeiſed as Priſoners, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a <hi>new addreſſe by way of Petition to the Parliament, intituled, The ſecond part of Englands new Chains diſcovered;</hi> We could not but wonder at the apprehending of M. <hi>Walwin</hi> about that, he having for ſome months paſt (that ever I could ſee or hear of) never been at any of our meetings, where any ſuch things were managed: But Adjutant General <hi>Stubber</hi> that was the Commander of the Party, coming then to view, I repaired to him, and deſired to ſee his Warrant, by vertue of which his men forced me out of my bed and habitation, from my Wife and children; and his Warrant he produced, which I read, he denying me a copy of it, though both there and at <hi>White-hall</hi> I earneſtly demanded it as my right: the ſubſtance of which, ſo neer as I can remember, is, From the Committee, <hi>commonly ſtiled the Councel of State,</hi> to authoriſe Sir <hi>Hardreſſe Waller, and Colonell Edward Whaley, or whom they ſhall appoint, to repair to any place whatſoever, where they ſhall hear Lieut. Col.</hi> John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, <hi>and M.</hi> Prince, <hi>M.</hi> Walwin, <hi>and M.</hi> Overton <hi>are, them to apprehend, and bring before the Councel of State, for ſuppoſition of high Treaſon, for compiling, &amp;c. a ſeditious and ſcandalous Pamphlet, intituled,</hi> The ſecond part of Englands new Chains diſcoverd. <hi>And for ſo doing, that ſhall be their Warrant.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed, John Bradſhaw Preſident.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And in the ſame paper is contained Sir <hi>Hardreſſe Wallers</hi> and Col. <hi>Whaley</hi>'s Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Deputation to Adjutant General <hi>Stubber</hi> to apprehend Mr. <hi>Walwin</hi> and my ſelf; who with his Officers, dealt abundantly more fairly with us, then I underſtand Lieut. Col <hi>Axtel</hi> dealt with Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> and Mr. <hi>Overton;</hi> From which Lieut. Col. if there had been any harmony in his ſpirit to his profeſſion, abundance more in point of civili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, might have been expected, then from the other, though he ſell much ſhort.</p>
               <p>But when we were in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, I was very earneſt with the Adjutant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and his Enſigne that apprehended me (as I underſtood by the Adjutant he was) that we might go to ſome place to drink our mornings draughts; and accordingly we went to the next door to the School houſe, where we had a large diſcourſe with the Officers, eſpecially about Mr. <hi>Deveniſh</hi>'s ſons; we underſtanding they had no Warrant at all to meddle with them in the leaſt, nor nothing to lay to their charge, but a private informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one <hi>Bull</hi> their Fathers tenant, between which parties there is a private difference; we told them, we could not but ſtand amazed, that any Officer of an Army durſt in ſuch a caſe apprehend the perſon of any Free-man of <hi>England,</hi> and of his own head and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, dragging him or them out of his houſe and habitation, like a Traitor, a Theef, or a Rogue; and they being aſhamed of what they had done to them, at our importunity, let both the young men go free. So away by water we three went to <hi>White hall</hi> with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant Gen. where we met with our friend M. <hi>Overton.</hi> And after we had ſtaid a: <hi>White hall</hi> till about 4 or 5 of the clock in the afternoon, we were by the foreſaid Adjutant carried to <hi>Darby-houſe,</hi> where, after about an hours ſtay, <hi>there were called in Lieut. Col.</hi> Goldegue, <hi>a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97720:3"/>
Coalyard keeper in Southwark, and as ſome of good quality of his neighbours do report him to have been no ſmall Perſonal Treaty man; and alſo Captain</hi> Williams, <hi>and M.</hi> Saul <hi>Shoe-maker, both of Southwark, who are ſaid to be the Devills 3. deputies, er informers againſt us;</hi> and after they were turned out, I was called in next, and the dore being opened, I marched into the Room with my hat on; and looking about me, I ſaw divers Members of the Houſe of Commons preſent, and ſo I put it off; and by Sergeant <hi>Dendy</hi> I was directed to go neer M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> that ſat as if he had been Chairman to the Gentlemen that were there preſent; between whom, and my ſelf, paſt to this following effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lievt. Col.</hi> Lilburn <hi>(ſaid he) here are ſome Votes of Parliament, that I am commanded by this Councel to acquaint you with;</hi> which were accordingly read, and which did contain the late publiſhed and printed Proclamation or Declaration, <hi>againſt the ſecond part of England New Chains diſcovered,</hi> with divers inſtructions and an unlimitted power given unto the Councel of State, to finde out the Authors and Promoters thereof, After the reading of which, M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſaid unto me, Sir, <hi>You have heard what hath been read unto you, and this Councell having information that you have a principle hand in compiling and promoting this Book,</hi> (ſhewing me the Book it ſelf,) <hi>therefore they have ſent for you, and are willing to hear you ſpeak for your ſelf.</hi> But I ſaw no Accuſer, proſecutor or witneſſe brought face to face, which were very ſtrange proceedings in my judgement.</p>
               <p>Well then M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> ſaid I, If it pleaſe you and theſe Gentlemen to afford me the ſame liberty the Cavaliers did at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when I was arraigned before them for my life, for levying war in the quarrel of the Common-wealth, againſt the late King and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (which was <hi>liberty of ſpeech to ſpeak my mind freely without interruption)</hi> I ſhall ſpeak and goe on, but without the liberty of ſpeach I ſhall not ſay a word more to you.</p>
               <p>To which he replied, <hi>That is already granted you, and therefore you may go on and ſpeak what you can or will ſay for your ſelf, if you pleaſe; or if you will not, you may hold your pyace and withdraw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then (ſaid I) M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> with your favour, thus. I am an Engliſhman born, bred, &amp; brought up, and England is a Nation Governed, Bounded, and Limited by Laws &amp; liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and for the Liberties of England, I have both fought and ſuffered much: but truely Sir, I judge it now infinitely below me, and the glory and excellency of my late actions, now to plead merit or deſert unto you, as though I were forced to fly to the merit of my former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to lay in a counter-ſcale, to weigh down your indignation againſt me, for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended late offences: No, Sir, I ſcorn it; I abhor it: And therefore Sir, I now ſtand before you, upon the bare, naked, and ſingle account of an Engliſhman, as though I had never ſaid, done, or acted thing that tendeth to the preſervation of the liberties thereof, but yet, have done any act that did put me out of a Legal capacity to claim the utmoſt punctilio, beneſit, &amp; priviledge that the laws &amp; liberties of England will afford to any of you here preſent, of any other man in the whole Nation: And the <hi>Laws and Liberties of England are my inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance and birth right.</hi> And in your late Declaration, publiſhed about four or five daies ago, wherein you lay down the grounds and reaſons (as I remember) <hi>of your doing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon the late King, and why you have aboliſhed Kingly Government, and the Houſe of Lords,</hi> you declare in effect the ſame; and promiſe to maintain the Lawes of England, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Peoples Liberties <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Their Declarations of the 9 <hi>of Feb.</hi> &amp; the 17 of <hi>March</hi> 1648, in which they poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively declare, they are fully reſolved to maintain, and ſhall and will preſerve and keep the fundamental Laws of this Nation, for and concerning the preſervation of the lives, properties and liberties of the people, with all things incident thereunto; but they of late years were never ſo good as their words; nor I am confident never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tead to be they having turned their backs upon common honeſty, upon the Lord their ſtrength, and made lies and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods their refuge and fortreſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeve them no more; for I will make it good they are worſe then the King was, whoſe head they have chopt off, for a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and Tyrant and thereby have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned themſelves, as deſerving his very puniſhment.</note> and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: And amongſt other things therein contained, you highly commend and extol <hi>the Petition of Right, made in the third year of the late King,</hi> as one of the moſt excellent and glorieſt Laws in reference to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple liberties that ever was made in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97720:4"/>
and you there very much blame, and cry out upon the King, for robbing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the people of England the benefit of that Law; and ſure I am (for I have read and ſtudied it) there is one clauſe in it that ſaith expreſly. <hi>That no Free man of England ought to be adjudged for life, limbe, liberty, or eſtate, but by the Laws already in being eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and declared:</hi> And truly Sir, if this be good and ſound Legal Doctrine (as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly it is, or elſe your own Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are falſe, and lies) I wonder what you Gentlemen are; For the declared and known Laws of England knows you not, neither by names nor qualifications as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons endowed with any power either to impriſon or try me, or the meaneſt Free-man of England; and truly, were it not that I know the faces of divers of you, and honour the perſons of ſome of you, as Members of the Houſe of Commons that have ſtood pretty firm in ſhaking times to the intereſt of the Nation; I ſhould wonder what you are, or before whom I am, &amp; ſhould not, in the leaſt honour or reverence you ſo much as with Civil Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, eſpecially conſidering the manner of my being brought before you, with armed men, and the manner of your cloſe ſitting, contrary to all courts of Juſtice, whoſe dores ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſtand wide open. M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> it may be the houſe of Commons hath paſt ſome Votes or Orders, to authoriſe you to ſit here for ſuch and ſuch ends as in their Orders may be declared: But that they have made any ſuch Votes or Orders, legally unknown to me, I never ſaw them. <hi>Its true, by common Fame you are bruted abroad and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iled a Councel of State,</hi> but its poſſible common Fame in this particular may as well tell me a lye as a truth; But admit common Fame do in this tell me a truth, and no lye, but that the Houſe of Commons in good earneſt hath made you a <hi>Councel of State,</hi> yet I know not what that is, becauſe the Law of England tells me nothing of ſuch a thing; and ſurely if a <hi>Councel of State</hi> were a Court of Juſtice, the Law would ſpeak ſomething of it: But I have read both old and new Lawes, yea all of late that it was poſſible to buy or hear of and they tell me not one word of you, and therefore I ſcarce know what to make of you, or what to think of you; but as Gentlemen that I know, I give you civill reſpect, and out of no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: But if you judge your ſelves to be a <hi>Councel of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and by vertue thereof think you have any power over me, I pray you ſhew me your Commiſſion, that I may know the better how to behave my ſelf before you. M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diſpute the Votes, or Orders of the preſent ſingle Houſe of Commons, in reference to their power, as binding Lawes to the people; yet admit them to be valid, legal, and good; their due circumſtances accompanying them: yet Sir, by the Law of England let me tell you, what the Houſe Votes, Orders, and Enacts within their walls, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me, I am not at all bound by them, nor in Law can take any cogniſance of them as Lawes, although 20 Members came out of the Houſe, and tell me ſuch things are done, till they be publiſhed and declared by ſound of Trumpet, Proclamation, or or the like, by a publike Officer or Magiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate in the publike and open places of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But truly Sir, I never ſaw any Law in Print or writing, that declares your power ſo proclaim'd or publiſhed; and therefore Sir, <hi>I know not what to make more of you</hi> then a company of private men, being neither able to own you for a Court of Juſtice, <hi>becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97720:4"/>
the Law ſpeaks nothing of you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> nor for a Councel of State, <hi>till I ſee, and read, or hear your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which I deſire (if you pleaſe) to be acquainted with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, give me leave further to aver unto you, and upon this Principle or Averment I will venture my life and being, and all I have in the world; <hi>That if the Houſe had by a Proclaimed and declared Law, Vote, or Order, made this Councel (as you call your ſelves) a Court of Juſtice, yet that proclaimed or declared Law, Vote, or Order, had been unjuſt and null, and void in itſelf;</hi> And my reaſon is, becauſe the Houſe it ſelf was never (neither now, nor in any age before) betruſted with a <hi>Law-executing power, but only with a Law making power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, Sir, I ſhould have look'd upon the people of this Nation as very fools, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they had betruſted the Parliament with a Law-executing power, and my reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, if they had ſo done, they had then choſen and impowred a Parliament to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them, but not to have preſerved them (which is againſt the very nature and end of the very being of Parliaments, <hi>they being by your own declared doctrine, choſen to provide for the peoples weale, but not for their wo,</hi> Firſt part <hi>Declarat. pag.</hi> 150, 266, 267, 269, 276, 279, 280, 304, 361, 382, 494, 696, 700, 716, 726.) And Sir, the reaſon of that reaſon is, becauſe its poſſible, if a Parliament ſhould execute the Law, they might do palpable inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> adminiſter it, and ſo the people would be robbed of their intended extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary benefit of Appeals; for in ſuch caſes, they muſt appeal to the Parliament either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf, or part of it ſelf; and can it ever be imagined they will ever condemn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or puniſh themſelves? <hi>nay, will they not rather judge themſelves bound in honour and ſafety to themſelves, to vote that man a Traytot, and deſtroy him, that ſhall ſo much as queſtion their actions, although formerly they have dealt never ſo unjuſtly with them?</hi> For this Sir, I am ſure, is very commonly practiſed now a dayes; and therefore the honeſty of former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the diſcharge of their truſt and duty in this particular, was ſuch, that they have declared, the power is not in them to judge or puniſh me, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the meaneſt free man in <hi>England,</hi> beeng no Member of their Houſe, although I ſhould beat or wound one of their Members nigh unto their door, going to the Houſe to diſcharge his duty; but I am to be ſent in all ſuch caſes to the Judge of the upper. <note n="*" place="margin">See 5. H. 4. 6. &amp; 11. H. 6. ch. 11. See alſo my plea againſt the Lords juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction before the Judges of the Kings Bench, <hi>called the Laws Funerall, pag. 8. 9.</hi> and my, grand plea againſt the Lords juru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, made before Mr. <hi>Maynard</hi> of the Houſe of Commons; and the four im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned Aldermen of <hi>London's</hi> plea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord jurisdiction, publiſhed by M. <hi>Lionel Hurbin, 1648.</hi>
                  </note> Bench, unto whom by Law they have given declared rules and direction in that particular how to behave himſelf, which be as evident for me to know as himſelf. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if reaſon and juſtice do not judg it convenient that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall not be Judges in ſuch particular caſes, that are of ſo neer concernment to themſelves, but yet hath others that are not of their Houſe, that are as well concerned as themſelves; much leſſe will reaſon or juſtice admit them to be judges in particular caſes that are farther remote ſtom their particular ſelves, and do meerly concern the Common-wealth; and ſure I am, Sir, this is the declared Statute Law of <hi>England</hi> and doth ſtand in full force at this hour, there being, I am ſure of it, no Law to repeal it, no not ſince the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſet up their new Common-wealth. Now, Sir, from all this I argue thus, <hi>that which is not inherent in the whole, cannot by the whole be derived or aſſigned to a part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it is not inherent, neither in the power nor authority of the whole Houſe of Commons, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily and originally to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ecute the Law, and therefore they cannot derive it to a part of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet Sir, with your favour, for all this, I would not be miſtaken, as though I maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97720:5"/>
ned the Parliament had no power to make a Court of Juſtice; for I do grant they may erect a Court of Juſtice to adminiſter the Law, <hi>provided, that the Judges conſiſt of perſons that are not Members of their Houſe; and provided, that the power they give them be univerſall;</hi> that is to ſay, to adminiſter the Law to all the people of <hi>England</hi> indefinitely, and not to two or three particular perſons ſolely, the laſt of which for them to do is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>And therefore I aver, that the High Court of Juſtice that ſate upon Duke</hi> Hamilton, <hi>the Earl of</hi> Holland, &amp;c. <hi>was no Court of Juſtice, but in the eye of the Law murdered thoſe Noble men; for which</hi> Bradſhaw <hi>and the reſt of his fellow Judges are not in the eye of the Law ſo excuſable as was</hi> Empſon <hi>and</hi> Dudly, <hi>that Sir</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook <hi>ſpeaks of in the 2. part. Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it. fo. 51. &amp; 3 part, f. 208. &amp; 4. part. Inſt. fol. 41. 196. 197. 198. who yet loſt their lives as Traitors, for ſubverters of the fundamentall Laws of</hi> England.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and altogether out of their power. And therfore Sir, to conclude this point; <hi>It being not in the power of the whole Parliament to execute the Law,</hi> they can give no power to you their Members to meddle with me in the caſe before you; For an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Court of Juſtice (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Adminiſtrator of the Law) is the only and ſole Judge in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and not you Gentlemen, no nor your whole Houſe it ſelf. And therefore, if you be honeſt men, and will be as good as your words, oaths and promiſes, (which are to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Laws, in reference to the peoples Liberties) I challenge at your hands the benefit of the Law, and not to be paſt upon otherwiſe in any kinde.</p>
               <p>For with your favour, Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> the fact that you ſuppoſe I have committed (for till it be judicially proved (and that muſt be before a legall Judge that hath cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of the fact) or confeſſed by my ſelf before the Judge; it is but a bare ſuppoſition) is either a crime, or no crime: <hi>a crime it cannot be, unleſſe it be a tranſgreſſion of a Law in being, before it was committed, acted or done;</hi> For, <hi>where there is no Law,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 4. 15. <hi>See the 4. part of the L.</hi> Cooks <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, ch. 1. High Court of Parl: fol. 37. 38. 39. 41. See alſo my printed Epiſtle to the Speaker, of the fourth of</hi> April, 1648. <hi>called the Priſoners plea for an</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus, p. 5 6. <hi>and</hi> Englands Birth-right, <hi>p. 1. 2. 3. 4. and the ſecond edition of my Epiſtle to Judge</hi> Reeves, <hi>p. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. and M.</hi> John Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>Truths Triumph, p. 11. 12. 13. 14. and Sir</hi> John Maynards Caſe <hi>truly ſtated, called</hi> The Laws Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>p.</hi> 9. 13. 14. 15. 16. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>there is no Tranſgreſſion</hi> And if it be a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of a Law, that Law provides a puniſhment for it, and by the Rules and method of that Law am I to be tryed, and by no other whatſoever, made <hi>ex poſt facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, Sir, if this be true, as undoubtedly it is; then I am ſure, you Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, have no power in Law to convene me before you for the pretended crime laid unto my charge; much leſſe to fetch me by force out of my habitation by the power of armed men: For Sir, let me tell you, The Law of <hi>England</hi> never made Colonels, Lieutenant Colonels, Captains, or Souldiers, either Bailiſſs, Conſtables, <note n="*" place="margin">See the Petition of Right, in the 3. C. R. and my Book called the peoples Prerogative, p. 44. 45. 46. 47. 48. &amp; 56. &amp;c. Yea, I ſay, that iſ the Generall take away by Martiall Law, the life of <hi>Laughorn, &amp;c.</hi> now in time of Peace, the Courts of Juſtice being open, he murders him or them, and ought to die therefore.</note> or Juſtices of Peace: And I cannot but wonder that you ſhould attach me in ſuch a manner as you have done, conſidering that I have all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long adhered to the Intereſt of the Nation againſt the common Enemy (as you call them) and never diſputed, nor contemned any Order or Summons from Parliament, or the moſt irregulareſt of their Committees, but always came to them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97720:5"/>
when they ſent for me, although their Warrant of Summons was never ſo illegall in the forme of it; and I have of late in a manner <hi>de die in diem,</hi> waited at the Houſe dore, and was there that day, the Votes you have read, paſt, till almoſt twelve a clock; <hi>and I am ſure there are ſome here preſent whoſe Couſcience I beleeve tells them, they are very much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this Book row before you)</hi> that ſaw me at the dore, and ſtared wiſhfully upon me as they went into the Houſe; and I cannot but wonder there could be no Civil Officer found to ſummon me to appear; but that now, when there is no viſible hoſtile enemy in the Nation, and all the Courts of Juſtice open, that you (that have no power at all over me) <hi>muſt ſend for me by a hundred or two hundred Armed Horſe and Foot, as though I were ſome monſtrous man, that with the breath of my mouth were able to deſtroy all the Civil Officers that ſhould come to apprehend me;</hi> Surely I had not endeavoured to fortifie my houſe, againſt you, neither had I betaken my ſelf to a Caſtle, or a defenced Garriſon in hoſtility againſt you, that you need to ſend a hundred or two hundred armed men to force me out of my houſe, from my wife and children, by four or five a clock in the morning, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting and afrighting of my wife and children: Surely <hi>I cannot but look upon this irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, unjuſt, and illegal hoſtile action of yours, as one of the fruits and iſſues of your new created Tyranny, to amuſe and debaſe my ſpirit, and the ſpirits of the People of this Free Nation, to fit me and them for bondage and ſlavery:</hi> This being the very practiſe of the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, as M. <hi>Pym</hi> in his declaration againſt him, doth notably obſerve. And Sir, give me leave further to tell you, that for divers hundreds of men that have often been in the field with their ſwords in their hands, to encounter with hoſtile enemies, and in their engagements have acquitted themſelves like men of valour, and come out of the field con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours; for theſe very men to put themſelves in Martial Array <hi>againſt four Miſe or But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terflyes,</hi> taking them captives, and as captives lead them through the ſtreets, me thinks is no ſmall diminution to their former Martial Atchievements and Trophies: And therefore to conclude this, <hi>I do here before you all, proteſt againſt your power and Jurisdiction over me in the caſe in controverſie; And alſo doe proteſt againſt your Warrant you iſſued out to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend me; And againſt all your martial and hoſtile acts committed towards me, as illegal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and tyrannical, and no way in Law to be juſtified:</hi> Further telling you that I ſaw moſt of the Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi>'s arraignment, and (if my memory fail me not) as little things as you have already done to me, were by your ſelves laid to his charge, as acts of Treaſon; For which I ſaw him loſe his head upon Tower-hill as a Traytor: And I doubt not for all this that is done unto me, but I ſhall live to ſee the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England</hi> firmly ſetled, in deſpite of the preſent great oppoſers thereof, and to their ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: and ſo M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> I have done with what I have now to ſay.</p>
               <p>Upon which M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> replied, <hi>Lieut. Col.</hi> Lilburn, <hi>you need not to have been ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and have ſpent ſo much time in making an Apologetical defence; for this Councel doth not go about to try you, or challenge any jurisdiction to try you, neither doe we ſo much as ask you a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in order to your tryal, and therefore you may correct your miſtake in that particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto which I ſaid, Sir, by your favour, if you challenge no Juriſdiction over me, no not ſo much as in order to a tryal, <hi>what do I here before you? or what do you in ſpeaking to me?</hi> But Sir, ſeeing I am now here, give me leave to ſay one word more, and that is this; I am not onely in time of peace (the Courts of Juſtice being all open) fetcht and forc't out of my houſe by multitudes of armed men, in an hoſtile manner, and carried as a captive up and down the ſtreets, contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry to all Law and Juſtice, but I am by force of Armes ſtill kept in their cuſtody, and it may be, may be intended to be ſent to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, who are no Guardians of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> no nor ſo much as the meaneſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators or executors of it, but ought to be ſubject to it themſelves, and to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97720:6"/>
of it, (as is cleer by the Petition of Right, &amp;c.) yea the General himſelf. And truly, Sir, I had rather die, then baſely betray my Liberties into their martiall fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers (who after their fighting for our Freedoms, would now deſtroy them, and tread them under their feet) that have nothing at all to do with me, nor any pretended or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all civill offender in <hi>England.</hi> I know not what you intend to do with me, neither do I much care; having learned long ſince to die, and rather for my Liberties, then in my bed. Its true, I am at preſent in no capacity effectually to diſpute your power, becauſe I am under guards of armed Masketiers; but I intreat you, if you will continue me a priſoner, that <hi>you will free me from the military Sword,</hi> and ſend me to ſome Civil Gaol; and I will at preſent in peace and quietneſſe obey your command, and go. And ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and was commanded to withdraw, which I did; and then Mr. <hi>William Walwin</hi> was called in: and while he was within, I gave unto my Comrades Mr. <hi>Prince,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Overton,</hi> and the reſt of the people, a ſummary account of what had paſt between me and them: And within a little time after Mr. <hi>Walwin</hi> came out again, and Mr. <hi>Overton</hi> was called in next: And at Mr. <hi>Walwin</hi>'s coming out he acquainted us what they ſaid to him, which was in a manner the ſame they ſaid to me; and all that he ſaid to them was but this, That he did not know why he was ſuſpected. To which Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> replyed, <hi>Is that all you have to ſay?</hi> And Mr. <hi>Walwin</hi> anſwered, Yes. So he was commanded to withdraw.</p>
               <p>And after M. <hi>Overton</hi> was come out, M. <hi>Prince</hi> was called in, and after he had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, they ſpent ſome time of debate among themſelves, and then I was called in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; <hi>So I marched in Sutable to my firſt poſture,</hi> and went cloſe to M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> who ſaid unto me to this effect: <hi>Lieut. Colonel</hi> Lilburn, <hi>this Councel hath conſidered what you have ſaid, and what they have been informed of concerning you, and alſo of that duty that lies upon them by the command of the Houſe, which enjoynes them to improve their utmoſt ability to find out the Author of this Book; and therefore to effect that end, they judge themſelves bound to demand of you this question: Whether you made not this Book, or were privie to the making of it or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after ſome pauſe, and wondring at the ſtrangeneſs of the queſion, I anſwered and ſaid, M. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> I cannot but ſtand amazed that you ſhould ask me ſuch a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this, at this time of the day, conſidering what you ſaid unto me at my firſt being before you; and conſidering it is now about eight yeers ago ſince this very Parliament annihilated the Court of <hi>Star-chamber, Councel board, and High Commiſſion,</hi> and that for ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings as theſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See the Acts that aboliſhed them, made in the</hi> 16 C. R. <hi>printed in my Book called</hi> The peoples Prerogative, <hi>p.</hi> 22. 23. 24. 25.</note>. And truly, Sir, I have been a conteſtor and ſufferer for the Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> theſe twelve years together, and I ſhould now look upon my ſelf as the baſeft fellow in the world, if now in one moment I ſhould undo all that I have been doing all this while; which I muſt of neceſſity do, if I ſhould anſwer you to queſtions againſt my ſelf: For in the firſt place, by anſwering this queſtion againſt my ſelf, I ſhould betray the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> in acknowledging you to have legall Juriſdiction over me, to try and adjudge me; which I have already proved to your faces you have not in the leaſt: And if you have forgot what you ſaid to me thereupon, yet I have not forgot what I ſaid to you. And Secondly, Sir, If I ſhould anſwer to queſtions againſt my ſelf, and ſo betray my ſelf, I ſhould do that which not onely Law, but Nature abhorrs: And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but <note n="*" place="margin">And well might I; for M. <hi>John Cook</hi> and M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were my Counſel at the Lords Bar, againſt the Star-chamber, the 13 of Feb. 1645. where M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> did moſt excellently oppen the Star-chamber injuſtice towards me; and at the reading of their firſt Sentence, he obſerved to the Lords, that that Sentence was <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> guilty of his own death; the ground whereof (ſaid he) being becauſe M. <hi>Lilburn</hi> refuſed to take an oath to anſwer to all ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions as ſhould be demanded of him, <hi>it being contrary to the Laws of God, Nature, and the Kingdom, for any man to be his own Accuſer:</hi> whoſe words you may more at large read in the printed Relation thereof, drawn up by M. <hi>John Cook,</hi> and my ſelf, p. 3. But he that condemned it in the Star-chamber, now practiſeth it in the Councel of State: but the more baſe and unworthy man he for ſo doing.</note> wonder that you your ſelves are not aſhamed to demand ſo iilegall and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97720:6"/>
unworthy a thing of me as this is, and therefore in ſhort, were it that I ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your power (which I do not in the leaſt) I would be hanged, before I would do ſo baſe and un-Engliſhman—like an Action, to betray my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; which I muſt of neceſſity do, in anſwering queſtions to accuſe my ſelf: But Sir, this I will ſay to you, My late Actions have not been done in a hole, or a corner, but on the houſe top, in the face of the Sun, before hundreds and ſome thouſands of people; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why ask you me any queſtions? Go to thoſe that have heard me, and ſeen me, and it is poſſible you may finde ſome hundreds of witneſſes to tell you what I have ſaid and done; for I hate holes and corners: My late Actions need no covers nor hidings, they have been more honeſt then ſo, and I am not ſorry for what I have done; for I did look well about me before I did what I did, and I am ready to lay down my life to juſtifie what I have done: And ſo much in anſwer to your queſtion.</p>
               <p>But now Sir, with your favour, one word more, to minde you again of what I ſaid before, in reference to my Martiall impriſonment: and truly Sir, I muſt tell you, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials of my Liberty, at this time, I ſhall not much diſpute; but for the Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of them I ſhall die. I am now in the Souldiers cuſtodie, where to continue in ſilence and patience, is abſolutely to betray my Liberty: for they have nothing to do with me, nor the meaneſt free man of <hi>England</hi> in this caſe: And beſides, Sir, they have no rules to walk by, but their wils and their ſwords, which are two dangerous things; it may be, I may be of an haſty cholerick temper, and not able nor willing to bear their affronts; and peradventure they may be as willing to put them upon me, as I am unwilling to bear them: and for you in this caſe to put fire and tinder together to burn up one another, will not be much commendable, nor tend much to the accompliſhment of your ends: But if, for all this, you ſhall ſend me back to the Military Sword again, either to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> or any other ſuch like gariſon'd place in <hi>England, I do ſolemnly proteſt before the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God of heaven and earth,</hi> I will fire it, and burn it down to the ground, if poſſibly I can, although I be burnt to aſhes with the flames thereof; for Sir, I ſay again, the Souldiers have nothing to do to be my Gaolers; and beſides, it is a <hi>maxime</hi> among the ſouldiers, <hi>That they muſt obey (without diſpute) all the Commands of their Officers, be they right or wrong;</hi> and it is alſo a <hi>maxime</hi> amongſt the Officers, <hi>That if they do not do it, they muſt hang for it:</hi> therefore if the Officers command them to cut my throat, they muſt either do it, or hang for it. And truly Sir, (looking wiſhly upon <hi>Cromwel,</hi> that ſate juſt againſt me) I muſt be plain with you, I have not found ſo much Honour, Honeſty, Juſtice or Conſcience in any of the principall Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, as to truſt <note n="*" place="margin">And truly, I am more then afraid honeſt Capt. <hi>Brav</hi> hath too much experience of this in <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, who though he be but barely committed thitther into ſafe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, yet (as I from very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>od hands am informed) the Tyrannicall Governour <hi>Whichcock, Cromwels</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth keep him cloſe priſoner, denying him the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Caſtle air, keeping not onely pen and ink from him, but alſo his friends and neceſſaries; with which cruelty &amp;c. he hath already almoſt murdered and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the honeſt man: in whoſe place were I, and ſo ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally and unjuſtly uſed, a flune, (if poſſibly I could) ſhould be the portion of my chamber, although I periſhed in it.</note> my life under their protection, or to think it can be ſafe under their immediate fingers; and therefore not knowing, nor much caring what you will do with me, I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97720:7"/>
earneſtly intreat you if you will again impriſon me, ſend me to a Civil Gaol that the Law knows, as New-gate, the Fleet, or the Gate-houſe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you ſend me to a Dungeon, thither will I go in peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without any further diſpute of your Authority; for when I come there, I know thoſe Gaolers have their bounds and limits ſet them by the Law, and I know how to carry my ſelf towards them, and what to expect from them; and if they do abuſe me, I know how in law to help my ſelf. And ſo Sir, I have ſaid what at preſent I have to ſay. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> commanded the Sergeant to put me out at another door, that ſo I ſhould no more go amongſt the people; and immediately Mr. <hi>Walwin</hi> was put out to me; and asking him what they ſaid to him, I found it to be the ſame in effect they ſaid to me, demanding the ſame fore-going queſtion of him, that they did of me: to which queſtion, (after ſome kinde of pauſe) he anſwered to this effect, <hi>That he could not but very much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be asked ſuch a queſtions however, that it was very much aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt his judgement and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to anſwer to queſtions of that nature, which concerned himſelf; that if he ſhould anſwer to it, he ſhould not onely betray his own Liberty, but the Liberties of all Engliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. which he could not do with a good conſcience; And he could not but exceedingly grieve at the dealing he had found that day; That being one who had always been ſo faithfull to the Parliament, and ſo well known to moſt of the Gentlemen there preſent, and that nevertheleſſe he ſhould be ſent for with a party of Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe and Foot, to the aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ighting of his Family and ruine of his credit; And that he could not be ſatisfied, but that it was very hard meaſure to be uſed thus upon ſuſpicion onely: And that if they did hold him under reſtraint from following his buſineſſe and occaſions, it might be his undoing, which he conceived they ought ſeriouſly to conſider of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſaid, He was to anſwer the queſtion, and that they did not ask it as in way of Tryal, ſo as to proceed in Judgment thereupon, but to report it to the Houſe. To which M. <hi>Walwin</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he had anſwered it ſo as he could with a good conſcience, and could make no other Anſwer,</hi> and ſo withdrew.</p>
               <p>And after he came out to me, Mr. <hi>Overton</hi> was next called in again, and then Mr. <hi>Prince;</hi> ſo after we were all come out, and all four in a room cloſe by them, all alone, I laid my ear to their door, and heard Lieutenant General <hi>Cromwel</hi> (I am ſure of it) very loud, thumping his fiſt upon the <hi>Councel Table,</hi> till it rang again, and heard him ſpeak in theſe very words, or to this effect: <hi>I tell you, Sir, you have no other way in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with theſe men, but to break them in pieces:</hi> and thumping upon the <hi>Councel Table</hi> again, he ſaid, <hi>Sir, Let me tell you that which is true, if you do not break them, they will break you; yea and bring all the guilt of the bloud and treaſure ſhed and ſpent in this Kingdom, upon your heads and ſhoulders; and fruſtrate and make void all that work that with ſo many yeers induſtry, toil and pains you have done, and ſo render you to all rationall men in the world, as the moſt contemptible generation of ſilly, low-ſpirited men in the earth, to be broken and routed by ſuch a deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cable contemptible genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men as they are: And therefore, Sir, I tell you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, you are neceſſitated to</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Reader, Obſerve I pray that this 40 headed Tyrant called the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State, are under an oath of Secreſie; ſo that if the <hi>Cromwelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Faction plot there the ruine and deſtruction of the Nation, or all the honeſt men in it, the reſt that do not conſent with them, muſt not reveal it. But the more unworthy men are they amongſt them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to be lovers of their Country to take ſuch a wicked oath of ſecreſie.</note> 
                  <hi>break them.</hi> But being a little diſturbed by the ſuppoſition of one of their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97720:7"/>
Meſſengers coming into the room, I could not ſo well hear the Anſwer to him, which I think was Colonel <hi>Ludlow</hi>'s voice, who preſſed to bail us; for I could very well hear him ſay, <hi>VVhat would you have more then ſecurity for them?</hi> Upon which diſcourſe of <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s, the bloud ran up and down my veins and I heartily wiſhed my ſelf in again amongſt them, <hi>(being ſcarce able to contain myſelf)</hi> that ſo I might have gone five or ſix ſtories higher then I did before, yea, as high as I intended when I came to their door, and to have particularly paid <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Haſlerig</hi> to the purpoſe, for their late venome, not onely againſt me in the Houſe, but my whole Family; <hi>Haſlerig</hi> ſaying (as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) in the open Houſe, <hi>There was never a one of the</hi> Lilburns <hi>Family fit or worthy to be a Conſtable in England;</hi> though I am confident there is not the worſt of us alive that have ſerved the Parliament, but he is an hundred times more juſt, honeſt and unſpotted then he himſelf, as in due time I ſhall make it appear, by Gods aſſiſtance (I hope) to his ſhame. But the fair carriage of the Gentlemen of the ſuppoſed Councel to me at the firſt, took off the height of the edge of my Spirit, and intended reſolution; which (it may be) they ſhall have the next time to this effect: <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u your ſelves have already voted the People, under God, the Fountain and Originall of all juſt Power;</hi> and if ſo, then none can make them Laws, but thoſe that are choſen, impowred and betruſted by them for that end: And if that be true, as undoubtedly it is, I deſire to know how the preſent Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen at <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> can make it appear they are the Peoples Repreſentatives, being rather choſen by the Will of him, whoſe head as a Tyrant and Traytor they have by their Wils chopt off, <hi>(I mean the King)</hi> then by the People: whoſe Will made the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough towns to chuſe Parliament men, and thereby robb'd about nineteen people of this Nation of their undubitable and inherent right, to give to a ſingle man in twenty for number (in reference to the whole Nation) a Monopoly to chuſe Parliament men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſ-franchiſing thereby the other nineteen: And if ſo in any meaſure, then upon their own declared Principles, they are no Repreſentative of the People, no nor was not at the firſt. Again, the King ſummoned them by his Writ (the iſſue of his will and pleaſure; and by vertue of that they ſit to this hour, and ſo are rather his Parliament, then the Peoples. Again, the King by his Will and pleaſure combines with them by an Act to make them a perpetual Parliament (one of the worſt and tyrannicalleſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever he did in his life) to ſit as long as they pleaſed; <hi>which he nor they had no pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r to do in the leaſt;</hi> the very conſtitution of Parliaments in England <hi>being to be once every yeer, or oftner, if need require. Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aere.</hi> Whether this Act of perpetuating this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Parliament men themſelves, beyond their Commiſſion, <hi>was not an act in them of the higheſt Treaſon in the world againſt the People and their Liberties by ſetting up themſelves an Arbitrary power over them for euer;</hi> which is the greateſt ſlavery can be exexciſed upon the ſons of men: Yea, and thereby razing the foundation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Parliament it ſelf: And if ſo, then this is null, if at the firſt it had been any thing.</p>
               <p>Again, if it ſhould be granted this Parliament at the beginning had <hi>a legal conſtitution from the people (the original and fountain of all just power)</hi> yet the Faction of a trayterous par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Officers of the Army, hath twice rebelled againſt the Parliament, and broke them to pieces and by force of Armes culled out whom they pleaſe, and impriſoned divers of them and laid nothing to their charge, and have left onely in a manner a few men, (beſides 12 of themſelves <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>General, Cromwel, Ireton, Harriſon, Fleetword, Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, Ingalsby, Haſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig, Conſtable, Fennick Walton,</hi> and <hi>Allen Treaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er;)</hi> of their own Faction behind them that will like Spanel-doggs ſerve their luſts and wills; yea ſome of the chiefeſt of them, <hi>viz. Ireton, Harriſon, &amp;c. yea, M. Holland himſelf, ſtiling them a mocke Parliament, a mocke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97720:8"/>
power at Winſor,</hi> yea it is yet their expreſſions at <hi>London;</hi> And if this be true that they are a mocke power and a mocke Parliament; then,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere,</hi> Whether in Law or Juſtice, (eſpecially conſidering they have fallen from all their many glorious promiſes, and have not done any one action that tends to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good of the people, and abſolutely degenerate into pure tyrany, and thereby, have loſt the eſſence and ſoul of authority, and are become but a dead and ſtincking Carkeſs) Can thoſe Gentlemen ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the Houſe, called the Houſe of Commons, be any other then a Factious company of men trayterouſly combined together with <hi>Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, Ireton,</hi> and <hi>Harriſon,</hi> to ſubdue the Lawes, Liberties, and Freedoms of <hi>Ergland;</hi> (for no one of them proteſts againſt the reſt) and to ſet up an abſolute and perfect Tyranny of the Sword, will and pleaſure, and abſolutely intend the deſtroying the Trade of the Nation, and the abſolute impoveriſhing the people thereof, to fit them to be their Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Slaves? And if ſo, then,</p>
               <p>Quere, <hi>Whether the Free-People of England, as well Souldiers as others, ought not to contemn all theſe mens commands, as invalid and illegal in themſelves, and as one man to riſe up againſt them as ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed traytors, theeves, robbers</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">For Magiſtacy going beyond its bounds and limits, and ſetting up their wills and luſts are no more Magiſtrates but Beares and Wolves, and ſo may be reſiſted; for theſe three things out of the Parliament and Armies Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I will prove to be good and ſound doctrine, conſonant to reaſon and ſcripture, <hi>viz.</hi> firſt that all Magiſteriall power in England what ever, are at moſt but Officers of truſt and expreſly bound up with this limitation, to be exerciſed for the good and wel fair of the truſters; Secondly, that it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that all, or any, of the ſeveral Magiſterial truſtees may forfeit their or its truſt; Thirdly, that in caſe of forfeting the Magiſterieal truſt, the truſters the people are diſobliged from their obedience and ſubjection, and may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doe the beſt they can for their own preſervation, and their Magiſtrates puniſhment.: See the firſt part of the Parliaments Declarations, pag. 81. 150. 201. 207. 264. 267. 270. 276. 304. 492. 494. 629. 690. 694. 696. 699. 700. 701. 726. 728. See the Armies booke, Declaration pag. 26. 34. 38. 39. 40, 41. 60. 61, 62 66. 141. 143, 144. See alſo King James opinion betwixt a Real King and a Tyrant, in his ſpeech to the Parliament 1609. See my Book called, <hi>The Out-crys of oppreſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> pag. 16. 17. 18. and regall Tyranny; pag. 32. 33, 34, 35. &amp;c. 59 60. 61, 62. but to behead the King for Tyranny and Treaſon, who was fenced about with the Letter of multitude of Lawes, puts this out of all diſpute.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; high way men, &amp; apprehend, ſecure and bring them to Juſtice in a new Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, choſen by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a juſt Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among the pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way in the world to preſerve the Nation but that alone; the three fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned men,</hi> viz. <hi>Cromwel, Ireton, and Harriſon,</hi> (the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall being but their ſtalking Horſ, and a Cipher) and there trayterous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <note n="**" place="margin">For the greateſt Traytors they are that ever were in this Nation, as upon the loſſe of my head l <hi>Ioh. Lilburn</hi> will by law under take to prove and make good before the next free and juſt Parliament to whom I hereby appeal.</note> having by their wills and Swords, got all the Swords of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> under their command; and the diſpoſing of all the great places in <hi>England</hi> by ſea and land, andalſo the pretended law executing power, by making among themſelves (contrary to the Lawes and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries of <note n="***" place="margin">For the people being in reaſon, justice and truth, as well as by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments late votes, the true fountain, and original of all juſt power, they ought not only in Reaſon, Right, and Juſtice, chuſe their own law makers, but all and every of their law executors, and to obey none what ſoever but of their own choice, and it is not only their right by reaſon and juſtice; but Sir <hi>Ed. Cooke</hi> in his ſecond part Institut. (publiſhed for good Law by this preſent houſe of Commons) declares and proves Fol. 174. 175. 558. 559. that by law it was and is, the peoples right to chuſe their Coroner, Juſtices, or conſervators of the Peace; as alſo their high Sheriff and Verderors of Foreſt; and ſaith he there expreſly for the time of War, there were likewiſe Leaders of the Countreys Souldiers of Ancient time, choſen by the Free-holders of the county: but it's true, the chiefeſt of theſe things were expreſly taken from the people, and inveſted in the King by the Statute of the 27. <hi>Hen. 3 chap. 24.</hi> and therefore Kingly government being aboliſhed, the right is returned into the people, the king or fountain of power, and cannot be exerciſed as a new deviſe by the Parliament although they were never ſo legally and Juſtly choſen by them without a conference with them thereupon, &amp; a power deputed to them for that end as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> declares in the 4 part of his Inſtitutes <hi>chap. High Court of Parliament. Fol. 14. 34.</hi> therefore I do hereby declare all the preſent Parliaments Juſtices, Sherifs <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be no Juſtices, Sherifs <hi>&amp;c.</hi> either in law or reaſon, but meer tyrants, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadors and uſurpers of their power and authority; and may very well in time come to be hanged for executing their pretended offices.</note> 
                  <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) all Judges,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97720:8"/>
Juſtices of Peace, Sheriffs, Bailiffes, Committee-men, &amp;c.</hi> to execute their wils and tyranny, walking by no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits or bounds, but their own wils and pleaſures: And trayterouſly aſſume unto themſelves a power to levie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people what money they pleaſe; and diſpoſe of it as they pleaſe, yea, even to buy knives to cut the peoples throats that pay the money to them, and to give no account for it till Dooms-day in the afternoone; they having already in their wills and power to diſpoſe of <hi>Kings, Queen, Princes, Dukes, and the reſt of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Revenues; Deans and Chapter lands, Biſhops lands, ſequeſtered Deliquents lands, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred Papiſts lands, Compoſitions of all ſorts, amounting to millions of money;</hi> beſides Exciſe, and Cuſtoms; yet this is not enough, although if rightly husbanded, it would conſtantly pay above one hundred thouſand men, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urniſh an anſwerrable Navy thereunto: But the people muſt now after their trades are loſt, and their eſtates ſpent to procure their liberties &amp; freedoms, be ſeſſed about 100000. pound a month, that <note n="****" place="margin">But ſaith there own Oracle, Sir <hi>Ed. Cook</hi> in the 4 part of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtutes chap. <hi>High Court of Parliament.</hi> Fol. 14. 34. It is alſo the Law and cuſtome of Parliament, that when any new device is moved on the Kings behalf in Parliament for his aid or the like, the Commons may anſwer, that they tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed the Kings eſtate, and are ready to aide the ſame, only in this new device they dare not agree without conference with their countries; whereby it appeareth (ſaith he) that ſuch conferences is warrantable by the law and cuſtome of Parliament, and this was do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in the Parliament of the <hi>9. Ed. 3.</hi> nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 5 but the preſent Parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume unto themſelves the regall office in the height, and therefore ought not to be their own carvers in reference to the peoples purſes, but ought to demand and obtain their conſents (eſpecially in time of peace) before they levie either 90000 pounds <hi>per</hi> month, or any ſuch like new device what ever; and therefore I know neither law equity or reaſon to compel the people to pay a penny of it; unleſſe they have a deſire to bring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ſame condition in reference to the preſent Parliament that the Egyptians were to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> when <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſo hard hearted as to make the Egyptians to pay ſo dear for b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead-corn, that it coſt them all their money, and all their cattle, yea all their lands and alſo themſelves for his ſlaves. <hi>Gen. 47. 14. 15. 16. &amp;c.</hi> for which tyranny God plagued him and his poſterity by making them ſlaves to the Egyptians afterwards.</note> ſo they may be able like ſo many cheaters and and State theeves, to give 6. 8. 10. 12. 14. 16000. pounds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peice over again to one another, as they have done already to divers of themſelves, to buy the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths lands one of another, (contrary to the duty of Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees, who by law nor equity can neither given or ſell to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother) or two or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97720:9"/>
three yeers purchaſe the true and valuable rate conſidered, as they have already done, and to give 4 or 5000l, <hi>per annum</hi> over again to King <hi>Crumwell.</hi> with ten or twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds worth of wood uponit) as they have done already out of the Earl of <hi>Worceſters</hi> eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beſides about four or five pounds a day he hath by his places of Lieut. Generall, and Colonel of Horſe in the Army (beſides the extraordinary advancement of many of his kindred, that ſo they might ſtick cloſe to him in his tyranny) although he were at the beginning of this Parliament but a poor man, yea, little better then a begger (to what he is now) as well as other of his neighbours.</p>
               <p>But to return, thoſe Gentlemen that would have had us bailed loſt the day, by one vote as we underſtood, for all their wicked oath of ſecrecy, and then about 12. at night, they broke up, (a fit hour for ſuch works of wickedneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 3. 19. 20. 21.) and we went into their pretended Secretary, and found our commitments made in theſe words, our names changed, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are to will and require you, to receive herewith into your cuſtody, the Perſon of</hi> Lieu. Col. John Lilburn, <hi>and him ſafely to keep in your Priſon of the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>untill you receive further order, he being committed to upon ſuſpition of high Treaſon, of which you are not to fail, and for which this ſhall be your ſufficient Warrant; given at the Councel of State at Derby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe 28. day of</hi> March, 1649.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>To the Lieu. of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed in the name, and by the Order of the Councel of State, appointed by authority of Parliament. <hi>Jo. Bradſhaw. Preſident.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Note that we were committed upon Wenſday their faſt day, being the beſt fruits that ever any of their faſts brought out amongſt them, viz. <hi>To ſinite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe.</hi> For the illegallity of this warrant, I ſhall not ſay much, becauſe it is like all the reſt of the warrants of the preſent Houſe of Commons, and their unjuſt Committees; whoſe Warrants are ſo ſufficiently anatomized by my <hi>quondam</hi> Comrade M. <hi>John Wildeman,</hi> (though much degenerated) his Books, called <hi>Truths Triumph, and the Laws ſubverſion,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sir <hi>John Maynard</hi>'s Caſe truly ſtated; and by my ſelf, in my late plea before the Judges of the Kings Bench, now in print, and intituled <hi>The Laws Funerall,</hi> that it is needleſſe to ſay any more of that particular; and therefore to them I refer the Reader.</p>
               <p>But to go on: When we had read our Warrants, we told Mr. <hi>Froſt,</hi> we would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the legality of them, becauſe we were under the force of Guards of armed Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers: So ſome time was ſpent to finde a man that would go with us to priſon; Captain <hi>Jenkins</hi> (as I remember his name) being Captain of the Guard, and my old and familiar acquaintance, was prevailed with by us, to take the charge upon him, who uſed us very civilly, and gave us leave that night (it being ſo late) to go home to our Wives, and took our words, with ſome other of our friends then preſent, to meet him in the morning at the Angel Tavern neer the Tower; which we did accordingly, and ſo marched with him into the Tower; where coming to the Lieutenants Houſe, and after ſalutes each of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with very much civility, the Lieutenant read his Warrants: and Mr. <hi>Walwin,</hi> as our appointed mouth, acquainted him that we were Engliſhmen; who had hazarded all we had for our Liberties and Freedoms for many yeers together, and were reſolved
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97720:9"/>
(though Priſoners) not to part with an inch of our Freedoms, that with ſtrugling for we could keep; and <hi>therefore we ſhould neither pay Fees nor chamber-rent, but what the Law did exactly require us; neither ſhould we eat or drink of our own caſt or charges, ſo long as we could faſt:</hi> telling him, it was our unqueſtionable right by Law, and the cuſtom of this place, to be provided for out of the publick Treaſure, although we had never ſo much money in our pockets of our own, <hi>which he granted to be true;</hi> and after ſome more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, I told him, we were not ſo irrationall, as to expect that he out of his own money ſhould provide for us: but the principall end of our diſcourſe with him was, to put words in his mouth from our ſelves (he being now our Guardian) to move the Parliament or Councel of State about us, which he hath acquainted us he did to the Councel of State; who, he ſaith, granted, the King or former times uſed to provide for the Priſoners: But I ſay, they will not be ſo juſt as he was in that particular; although they have taken off his head for tyranny, yet they muſt and will be greater Tyrants then he; yea, <hi>and they have reſolved upon the Queſtion, that he ſhall be a Traytor that ſhall but tell them of their Tyranny, although it be never ſo viſible:</hi> But let me tell them, that ſaying of Mr. <hi>John Cook</hi> their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor general, in his Book, called the Kings caſe ſtated, is moſt true, That <hi>in condemning the King for tyranny, they have already paſt Sentence againſt themſelves when they tyrannize.</hi> But I ſay, and will make it good upon my life before competent Judges, that they are greater Tyrants then the King was, and the Ring-leaders of them better deſerved his puniſhment of loſſe of their heads, then he did; for he never made ſuch profeſſions of Libertie and Juſtice to the People as they have done, but always maintained the people had no ſhare in Government; and that for his miſgovernment he was accountable to none but God: and yet I will juſtifie it, their actions are as wicked as his: yea, I will maintain it, that the cruel tyrant Duke <hi>D'Alva</hi> ſo much mentioned in <hi>Edmond Grimſtons</hi> generall Hiſtory of the <hi>Neather-Lands, lib.</hi> 9. who with his High Court of Juſtice, or Counſell of State, put above eighteen thouſand to death under pretence of Juſtice in leſs then five yeers, <hi>fol.</hi> 435. 462. was more excuſable then the Leaders of theſe men: Yea, bloudy Qu. <hi>Mary</hi> (in compariſon) was a Saint to theſe men, who never went about to burn or hang the Martyrs, but for tranſgreſſing a Law in being; yea, and let them enjoy open tryals according to Law: but theſe men would hang us for Traitors, although we have tranſgreſſed none of their Laws; yea, and in the night, contrary to Law, in a cloſe room examine us againſt our ſelves, without producing face to face either proſecutor, accuſer or witneſſe, yea, or ſo much as laying any crime unto our charge, our chiefeſt Adverſaries being our Judges. Wherefore, <hi>Hear O heavens, and give ear O earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So now I have brought the Reader to my old contented lodging in the Tower; where, within two or three days of our arrivall there, came one M. <hi>Richardſon</hi> a Preacher amongſt thoſe unnatural, un-Engliſh-like men, that would now help to deſtroy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and the firſt promoters in <hi>England</hi> (as <hi>Cromwels</hi> beagles to do his pleaſure) of the firſt Petition for a perſonal Treaty, almoſt two yeers ago, <hi>and commonly ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Preachers to the ſeven Churches of Anabaptiſts:</hi> which <hi>Richardſon,</hi> pretending a great deal of affection to the Common-wealth, to <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and to us; and preſt very hard for union and peace (and yet by his petition ſince this, endeavours to hang us) tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, men cryed mightily out upon us abroad for grand diſturbers, that ſought <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi> bloud for all his good Service to the Nation, and that would center nowhere, <hi>but meerly laboured to pull down thoſe in power, to ſet up our ſelves:</hi> And after a little diſcourſe with him, being all four preſent, and retorting all he ſaid back upon thoſe he ſeemed to plead for, before ſeverall witneſſes, we appealed to his own conſcience to this effect,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97720:10"/>
whether thoſe could intend any hurt or tyranny to the people, that deſire, and earneſtly endeavoures for many years together, that all Magiſtrates hands might be bound and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by a juſt law and rule, with a penalty annexed unto it, that in caſe they out-ſtripe their rule, they might forfeit life and eſtate therefore, and that all Magiſtrates might be choſen by the free people of this Nation by common conſent, according to their undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable right, and often removed, that ſo they might not be like ſtanding waters, ſubject to corruption; and that the people might have a plain eaſie, ſhort, and known Rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves to walk by, adminiſtred in their own Countries; but ſuch men were all we; and therefore juſtly could not be ſtiled diſturbers of any, but onely ſuch as ſought to rule over the people by their abſolute Wills and pleaſures, and would have no bounds or limits but their luſts, and ſo ſought to ſet up a perfect tyranny, which we abſolutely did, and ſtill do charge upon the great men in the Army, <hi>viz. Cromwel, Ireton, Haſelrig, Harriſon</hi> &amp;c. and are ready before indifferent Judges to make it good. And as for ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves, we need no other witneſſes but ſome of our preſent adverſaries in the Houſe, whoſe great proffered places, and courtſhip by themſelves and their Agents ſome of us have from time to time ſlighted, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rned, and contemned, <hi>till they would conclude to come to a declared and reſolved center, by a juſt Agreement of the People;</hi> there being no other way now in the world <hi>to make this Nation free, happy or ſafe,</hi> but that alone. And as for <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi> blood, although he had dealt baſely enough with ſome of us in times by-paſt, by thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after ours, without cauſe; of whom (if revenge had been our deſire) we could have had it the laſt yeer to the purpoſe, eſpecially <hi>when his quondam Darling, Maj.</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington, <hi>(Maj. to his own Regiment) impeached him of Treafon to both Houſes:</hi> yet ſo deer was the good of our Native Country to us, to whom we judged him then a ſerviceable Inſtrument to ballance the Scots, that we laid all revenge aſide, hoping <hi>his often diſſembled Repentance was real indeed;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Holland</hi> himſelf (now his favorite) if his 1000. or 1500. l. <hi>per annum</hi> of the Kings Lands, that now he injoys, did not make him forget himſelf, can ſufficiently teſtifie and witneſs our unwearied and hazardous Activity for <hi>Cromwels</hi> particular preſervation the laſt yeer, when his great friends in the Houſe durſt not publickly ſpeak for him.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid we will Center nowhere, we have too juſt cauſe to charge that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; the whole ſtream of all our Actions (as we told <hi>Richardſon)</hi> being a continued De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of our earneſt deſires to come to a determinate and fixed center: one of us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſufficient propoſitions to that purpoſe to the Councel of State at our laſt being there, and all our many and late proffers as to that perticular, they have hitherto rejected, as no ways conſiſtent with their tyrannical and ſelviſh ends and deſignes: and given us no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer in effect, but the ſending our bodies priſoners to the Tower: and therefore we judged it infinitely below us (as we told him) and that glorious cauſe, <hi>the Peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Freedoms, that we are now in bonds for)</hi> and for which we ſuffer, to ſend any meſſage but a defiance by him or any other to them. Yet to let him know (as one we judged honeſt, and our friend) we were men of reaſon, moderation, and juſtice, and ſought nothing particularly for our ſelves more then our common ſhare in the common freedom, tranquillity, and peace of the land of our Nativity: We would let him know, we had a two fold Center, and if he pleaſed of and from himſelf to let our Adverſaries know, we were willing our adverſaries ſhould have their choiſe to which of the two they would hold us to.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſaid we in the firſt place, <hi>The Officers of the Army have already compiled, and publiſhed to the view of the Nation, an Agreement of the people,</hi> which they have preſented
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97720:10"/>
to the preſent Parliament; againſt which we make ſome exceptions, which exceptions are contained in our Addreſſes: Now let them but mend their Agreement according to exceptions, and ſo far as all our intereſt extends in the whole Nation, we will acquieſce and reſt there, and be at peace with them, and live and dye with them in the purſuance of thoſe ends; and be content for <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Iretons</hi> ſecurity, &amp;c. for the blood of war ſhed in time of peace at <hi>Ware,</hi> or any thing elſe; and to free our ſelves that we thirſt after none of their blood, but onely our juſt Liberties (without which we can never ſit down in peace) That there ſhall be a clauſe, <hi>to bury all things in oblivion, as to life and liberty, excepting one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtate;</hi> that ſo the Common-wealth may have an account of their monies in Treaſurers hands, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, if they judge our exceptions againſt their Agreement (or any one of them) irrational, let them chuſe any 4 men in England, &amp; let <hi>Crumwel &amp; Ireton be 2 of them,</hi> &amp; take the other 2 where they pleaſe, in the whole Nation, &amp; we 4 now in priſon, wil argue the caſe in reaſon with them, and if we can agree, there is an end, as to us, &amp; all our intereſt; but in caſe we cannot, let them (ſaid we all) chuſe any 2 membes of the Houſe of Commons, &amp; we will chuſe 2. more, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Alex. Rigby,</hi> &amp; Col. <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> &amp; to be final umpires betwixt us: &amp; what they, or the major part of them determine, as to us (in relation to an <hi>Agreement)</hi> and all our intereſt in the whole land, we will acquieſce in, be content with, and ſtand to without wavering: and this we conceive to be as rational, juſt, and fair, as can be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any men upon earth: and I for my part, ſay and proteſt before the Almighty, I will yet ſtand to this, and if this will content them, I have done; if not, fall back, fall edge, let them do their worſt I for my part bid defiance to them, <hi>aſſuredly knowing, they can do no more to me, then the Devil did to Job;</hi> for reſolved by Gods aſſiſtance I am, to ſpend my heart bloud againſt them, if they will not condeſend to a juſt <hi>Agreement</hi> that may be good for the whole Nation; that ſo we may have a ſpeedy new and as equall a Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative as may be, choſen by thoſe that have not fought againſt their freedoms, although I am as deſirous the Cavaliers ſhould enjoy the benefit of the Law, for the protection of their perſons and eſtates, as well as my ſelf. <hi>I know they have an Army at command, but if every hair on the head of that Officer or Souldier they have at their command were a legion of men, I would fear them no more then ſo many ſtraws;</hi> for the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> is my rock and defence, under the aſſured ſhelter of whoſe wings, I am ſafe and ſecure, <hi>and therefore will ſing and be merry;</hi> and do hereby ſound an eternal trumpet of defiance to all the men and devils in the earth and hell, but onely thoſe men who have the image of God in them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it among men, by their <hi>juſt, honeſt, merciful and righteous actions.</hi> And as for all thoſe vild aſpertions their ſaint-like Agents have fixed upon me of late, I know <hi>before God none is righteous no not one, but only he that is clothed with the glorious righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which I aſſuredly know my ſoul hath been, and now is clothed with, in the ſtrength of which I have walked for above 12 years together, and through the ſtrength of which, I have been able at any time in all that time, to lay down my life in a quarter of an hours warning. But as to man I bid defiance to all my Adverſaries upon earth, to ſearch my wayes and goings with a candle, and to lay any one baſe Action to my charge in any kind whatſoever, ſince the firſt day that I viſibly made profeſſion of the fear of God, which is now about twelve yeers; yea, I bid defiance to him or them, to proclaim it upon the houſe top, provided he will ſet his hand to it, and proclaim a publike place, where before indifferent men, in the face of the Sun, his accuſation may be ſcand; yea, I here declare, that if any man or woman in England, either in reference to my publike actions, to the States money, or in reference to my private dealings in the world ſhall come in and prove againſt me, that ever I defrauded him, or her of twelve pence, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97720:11"/>
for every twelve pence that I have ſo done, I will make him or her twenty ſhillings worth of amends, ſo far as all the eſtate I have in the world will extend.</p>
               <p>Courteous Reader, and deer Countryman, excuſe I beſeech thee my boaſting and glorying, for I am neceſſitated to it, my adverſaries baſe and lying calumniations puting me upon it, and <note place="margin">Iohn Lilburn, <hi>that never yet changed his principles from better to worſe, nor could never be threatned out of them, nor courted from them, that never feared the rich nor mighty, nor never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the poor nor needy, but alwayes hath and hopes by Gods goodneſs to continue ſemper idem.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> did it before me: and ſo I am thine, if thou art for the juſt Freedoms and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the land of thy Nativity,</p>
               <p>From my rejoycing captivity (for bearing witneſſe againſt Tyranny in whomſoever I find it) in the Tower of London <hi>April</hi> 3. 1649</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CUrteous Reader, I have much wondred with my ſelf, what ſhould make moſt of the Preachers in the Anabaptiſts Congregations ſo mad at us four, as this day to deliver ſo baſe a Petition, in the intention of it againſt us all four; (who have been as hazardous Sticklers for their particular liberties, as any be in England) and never put a provocation upon them that I know of, eſpecially, conſidering the moſt, if not all their Congregations, (as from divers of their own member I am informed) sproteſted againſt their intentions openly in their Congregations, upon the Lords day laſt, and I am further certainly informed that the aforeſaid Petition the Preachers delivered, is not that which was read by themſelves amongſt the people; but another of their own framing ſince, which I cannot hear was ever read in any one of their Congregations: ſo that for the Preachers viz. M.</hi> Kiffin, <hi>M.</hi> Spilsbury, <hi>M.</hi> Patience, <hi>M.</hi> Draps, <hi>M.</hi> Richardſon, <hi>M.</hi> Conſtant, M. Wayd the Schoolemaſter, &amp;c. <hi>to deliver it to the Parliament in the name of their Congregations; they have delivered a lye and a falſhood, and are a pack of fauning daubing knaves for ſo doing, but as I underſtand from one of</hi> M. Kiffins <hi>members,</hi> Kiffin <hi>himſelf did ingenuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe upon the Lords day laſt, in his open Congregation, that he was put upon the doing of what he did by ſome Parliament men, who he perceived were willing and deſirous to be rid of us four, ſo they might come off handſomely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out too much loſſe of credit to themſelves: and therefore intended to take a riſe from their Pettition to free us, and for that end it was, that in their Petition read in the Congregations, after they had ſufficiently beſpattered us, yet in the concluſion they beg mercy for us; becauſe we had been formerly active for the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97720:11"/>
Publick. Secondly, I have been lately told, Some of the Congregationall Preachers are very mad at a late publiſhed and licenſed Book, ſold in Popes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head Alley, and the blue Anchor in Cornhill, intituled,</hi> The vanity of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Churches; <hi>ſuppoſing it to be the Pen of ſome of our Friends, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of revenge might petition againſt us: I confeſſe, I have within a few hours ſeen and read the Book, and not before; and muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe, it is one of the ſhrewdeſt Books that ever I read in my life, and do beleeve it may be poſſible they may be netled to the purpoſe at it; but I wiſh every honeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed man in England would ſeriouſly read it over.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 4. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Lilburn.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I Shall deſire to acquaint the Reader, that when the Title page of the fore-going Book was firſt ſet, there was an abſolute determination to have re-printed all our Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions together; but for ſome weighty reaſons the intentions are altered; and becauſe I underſtand that the fury, rage and bloud-thirſtineſſe of <hi>Cromwell, Ireton, Haſterig,</hi> and <hi>Harriſon</hi> is moſt at me, right or wrong to deſtroy me and have my bloud, I am determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by Gods aſſiſtance, to fill their hands as full with my own pen, as all the brains I have can fill them; and to make them pay a valuable price, if poſſibly I can, for every hair of my head. And in order to my future intentions, I ſhall here annex my Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes againſt the Biſhops, when they had like to have murdered me in the Fleet, being printed at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> 1639, intituled</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A CRY FOR JUSTICE: OR; <hi>An Epiſtle written by</hi> John Lilburn, To all the grave and worthy Citizens of the famous City of <hi>London,</hi> but eſpecially to the Right honorable <hi>Maurice Abbot,</hi> Lord Maior thereof,</head>
                     <head type="sub">The moſt miſerable and lamentable complaint of that inhumane, barbarous, ſavage and unparalell'd cruelty and tyranny, that is cauſeleſly, unjuſtly, and wrongfully exerciſed upon me <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hn Lilburn</hi> a faithfull Subject to my Prince, Country, and a Prentiſe of this Honorable City, though now a moſt deplorable cloſe priſoner in the common Gaol of the Fleet. 1639.</head>
                     <p>MOſt Honorable and Noble Lord, The chief cauſe wherefore God the wiſe Governour of Heaven and Earth, did appoint Magiſtrates, was for the good of the ſons of men, and that they ſhould do Juſtice betwixt a man and his neighbour, and that they ſhould hear the grievances of the oppreſſed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the cruelty of their oppreſſors.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97720:12"/>
That wrong, violence and injuſtice that I have ſuffered, would be now too long to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in particular: but it being ſo inſupportable, made me to publiſh it abroad unto the view of the world, to the perpetuall infamy of my tormentors, the chief of which are the traiterous, bloody, murthering Prelates.</p>
                     <p>The ſtory of my former miſery and wrongs you may, if you pleaſe, read at large in three ſeverall Books of mine now in print, and publiſhed to the view of England, Scotland, Ireland and Holland. They are called <hi>My unjuſt Cenſure in the Star-chamber, My Speech at the Pillory,</hi> and <hi>My mournſull Lamentations.</hi> I have not ſeen them ſince they were put in print, becauſe the Prelate of Canterbury wrongfully detains well nigh two thouſand of them from me: but there are ſtill many thouſands of them behinde; and I doubt not but ſome, who pities my afflicted eſtate, will convey ſome of them unto your Lordſhips hands: In the laſt of which I have proved, that I am more cruelly dealt with, then bloudy <hi>Bonner</hi> dealt with the poor Saints and Martyrs in Queen <hi>Marys</hi> dayes, and that I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed that which in England was never yet denyed to any Traytor that ever I read of. And in it I accuſe <hi>William Laud</hi> the Prelate of Canterbury for High Treaſon; the which I did a yeer agone before Sir <hi>John Banks</hi> Knight, and will ſtill venture my life upon the proof thereof, if I may have a Legall proceeding. One ground of my accuſation is this; the, Parliament Laws and Statutes of this Land, as the 25 and 37 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and the firſt of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and the firſt and 27 of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> doth enact to this effect, <hi>That whoſoever goes about to ſet up or challenge any forrain or domeſtick Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, but what doth immediately flow and come from the Imperiall Crown, is</hi> (ipſo facto) <hi>a Traitor, and ought to die without the benefit of Clergie,</hi> as more at large in them you may read. Now the Biſhop of Canterbury and the reſt of his mercileſſe brethren, about four yeers agone, in the Cenſure of that Noble Doctor <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> (now of late much degenerate) there in their open Court at Lambeth, renounced the King and his Authority, and ſaid, <hi>They were not behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him for their Epiſcopall Juriſdiction; for they were made Biſhops by Jeſus Chriſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by the holy Ghoſt, and they had their thrones, and were before Chriſtian Kings, and they held the Crowns of Kings upon their heads; and their Maxime was, No Biſhop, no King.</hi> And if this be not treaſon, then I think there was never any committed: And this, with much more to this effect, Doctor <hi>Baſtwick</hi> doth declare in his anſwer to Sir <hi>John Banks</hi> his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (as you may read in the tenth and eleventh pages thereof.) And for this (moſt Noble Lord) was I, againſt all Law and Juſtice, laid in irons for a long time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in a moſt inhumane manner, and lock'd up cloſe priſoner for theſe twelve months together, againſt all Law, and to the violating of the Subjects Libertie: for by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Statutes of this Land, which are ſtill in force, but onely the execution of them is thrown in the kennell, neither the Lord Keeper, nor any others ought to commit any of the Kings Subjects cloſe priſoners, unleſs either for Felony or Treaſon, and onely in caſe of an extraordinary crime; and then they muſt forthwith bring them to their tryall: But by cloſe impriſonment the Law doth not mean that the Kings Subjects ſhould be locked up in rooms; much leſſe, that their friends ſhould not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to come to ſpeak with them, and bring them victuals to preſerve their lives, as grave Judge <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ok,</hi> not long ſince, in his Speech at Weſtminſter-Hall did prove, when he pleaded for the Subjects Liberty. <hi>But contrary to the Parliament Laws, yea, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Heathens and Pagans, I am locks up cloſe all alone, and cannot be ſuffered to come to a juſt tryall;</hi> but am kept up ſo cloſe, that my friends and acquaintance that bring me relief (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long ſince deſerted of my Kindred) are not ſuffered to come at me, but are ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with that they bring me, with all the abuſes, reproaches, and revilings that poſſible may be, by my Keeper. And one that came unto me he hath beaten, and others he hath
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97720:12"/>
threatned to kick if they come any more to me; and to others of them he hath moſt faſly and ſlinderouſly reviled me, calling me Rebell and Traytor, telling them that no victuals ſhould come at me: ſo that I am forced daily, in regard of barbarous cruelty, to cry out aloud at my iron grate, to the priſoners and ſtrangers, to let them know the height of my miſery wherein I live: and yet no redreſſe can I have, but daily more and more cruelty is exerciſed upon me, and many grievous threats from bloudy murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Morry</hi> my keeper, who threatens to hamper me, and lock my head and legs together for my complaining: This he did the laſt Lords day at night, and alſo offered to beat me with his keys, in ſo much, that at ten a clock at night I was forced to cry out to the priſoners of it. And in this moſt miſerable condition do I remain, though I have been dangerouſly ſick almoſt theſe eleven months, which many times hath brought me even unto deaths door; and in regard of my exceeding extremity of pain in my head, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my long cloſeneſſe ever ſince Candlemaſs Term was twelve months, and my cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell torments beſides, I have been conſtrained (for to get a little eaſe of my extream pain, which in ſudden fits takes me for two or three hours together) to be tied to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of Phyſick uſually once in fourteen dayes, and ſometimes oftner: And though of late I had a little liberty to walk once a day in the common priſon yard; yet I am now deprived of it by the Warden for complaining of my keepers cruelty, and his ſhamefull abuſing me, and my friends which did but come to look upon me; with whom this was my greateſt diſcourſe, that I had tied my ſelf by promiſe, before I could get that little liberty of walking, that I would not talk with any Friends; therefore I deſired them not to be offended, for I durſt not talk with them: Yet becauſe they came but to ſee me, I was deprived of it; and alſo they that looked to me in my ſickneſſe and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe kept from me; ſo that now in my weakneſs I have none to look to me. In my <hi>Grievous and mournfull Complaint</hi> already publiſhed, I have a little touched the Wardens galled conſcience for his cruell oppreſſions: wherefore he in revenge (it ſeems) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to murther me, leſt I ſhould by my juſt complaints make it coſt him as dear as the ſalving up of his wickedneſſe did, when he was laſt called to an account; for I have heard the priſoners with open mouth proclaim it, that for making his peace, he gave to the Barl of <hi>Bohon</hi> ten thouſand pounds, and to the fore-man of the Jury one thouſand pounds; for which his conſcience being troubled, he revealed it upon his death bed: And alſo to an Officer five hundred pounds to raſe out ſome things which were upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: yea, I have heard the poor Priſoners proclaim it aloud, that he cozens them of above ſeven hundred pounds a yeer which belongs to them; and allows them but a ſmall pittance, upon which they are not able to live; and ſome of them have ſeverall times in the open Chappel cryed out to the Gentlemen priſoners, that they are ready to ſtarve and periſh for want of food; yea, ſo great hath been the barbarous cruelty of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the poor, that (if the Priſoners reports may be beleeved) poor men here have been forced, for want of food, to eat their own dung: And this had been my own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in likelyhood, had not God raiſed up ſome compaſſionate Friends, that were meer ſtrangers unto me before my ſufferings; ſome of which, through all difficulties and reproaches from my Keeper, have brought me food. And though the poor have not by the Wardens means the tenth part of their due, yet to leſſen that ſmall means which the poor hitherto hath had (ſome of which have nothing elſe in the world to live upon) he hath of late added unto them ſo many more, (ſome of which are men of able eſtates) which he hath put upon the charity, contrary to their Orders, purpoſely to ſtarve the poor indeed: yea, he hath by force put upon the charity <hi>Henry</hi> the Hangman, who is under-Turn-key, and hath forty pound land a yeer, as he himſelf confeſſeth; and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97720:13"/>
whoſe vailes beſides, as I have heard the priſoners ſay, are ſome times better worth then three ſhillings a day; and this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the warden hath done for him, becauſe he is ſo officious and ready in beating and abuſing the poor diſtreſſed priſoners, that cry out of the wardons cruelty; and not only the poor priſoners, but alſo ſome of thoſe that come to viſit and relievethem, ſome of which he hath beat, and threatned to kick others.</p>
                     <p>I have heard the priſoners affirm that the revenues of the Fleet hath been caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p to be above threeſcore thouſand pounds a yeer; oh therefore the height of cruelty not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell'd, I think amongſt the ſavage, and barbarous Heathens and Pagans, and which mightily crys unto your Honer, now in our Soveraigns abſence, for the wellfare of the City, betimes to be looked unto, and with the aſſiſtance of the Noble Lord Protector, to examine out the truth of things, that poor oppreſſed men may have ſpeedy redreſs of their wrongs; the greateſt part of which, ariſeth by reaſon of the wardens greatneſſe with the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and the Lord Keeper, ſo that they dare not for fear (as I have heard ſome of them ſay) complain of him.</p>
                     <p>Beſides my Lord it is notoriouſly known, that <hi>John Morry</hi> my upper keeper hath been arraigned at Newgate for murthering a priſoner here in former times, and I think here are other freſh things againſt him, if poor priſoners might be heard and have juſtice, which would bear another inditement, and at leaſt manifeſt him to be too too bloudy a man to have the keeping of poor innocent men; For ſome in this priſon, as it is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported have been ſecretly poyſoned and loſt their lives upon it, and others with eating garlike, and like antidotes have expelled it, and are yet living here to juſtifie the ſame; and my dogged under keeper hath been a hangman; whereupon the priſoners at their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings out with him, do ſay this verſe to his face <hi>(vix) Morry</hi> the Iriſh pedler, and <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the hangman of Cambridge-Shiere, and by theſe two bloody<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men, from both of which I have received unſufferable wrongs, my Adverſaries intend I ſhall be killed in a corner.</p>
                     <p>Becauſe of my untainted innocency, they dare not bring me to a legall publike tryal to the view of the Kingdom; wherefore I am forced by reaſon of intolerable cruely injuſtice and wrong, to cry out unto your Honour, as I have often done at my grate, murther, murther, murther; therefore hear O Heavens, and give care O Earth, and all ye that hear or read this my juſt complaint and lamentation, bear witneſſe to future generations, that I cry out of violence, wrong, injuſtice, cruelty, and inhumanity, that I ſuffer from the trayterous Biſhop, and the unjuſt Lord Keeper, old Sir <hi>Henry Vaine,</hi> and their bloody Jaylours, which do and will execute their commands, be they never ſo unjuſt and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And how that for my zeal and courage for my God and his truth and glory, and for my ardent love to my Prince and Country, and for my ſtrong de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ire and indeavour for the proſperity and flouriſhing eſtate of this renowned City, the Metropolis of England, I am like to loſe my life and blood by murthering cruelty in cloſe Impriſonment; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, oh all ye brave and worthy Citizens, ſave, help and reſcue me a poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and greatly oppreſſed young man, from the devouring pawes of devouring Lioniſh men.</p>
                     <p>Now my Honorable Lord, I come to make my humble ſupplication unto your ſelf, which is this; that you would be pleaſed to take my moſt deplorable condition into your grave and ſerious conſideration, and after your conſultation about it, with your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull brethren the Aldermen of this City, acquaint the honourable Lord protector that noble and courteous Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> with it (who in part knows it already) but alas alas, I am long ſince deſerted of my kindred and friends, ſo that I have none that dare follow my buſineſſe for me; wherefore I am like ſhortly to periſh in my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97720:13"/>
great diſtreſs unleſs your Lorſhips be pleaſed in this particular to do ſomething for me.</p>
                     <p>I deſire from your Honours neitheir ſilver nor gold, for alas at preſent it would do me no pleaſure; for had I all treaſure in the world to buy me victuals, and want a ſtomack when I ſhould have them, they would nothing avail me: and yet ſo lamentable is my condition, by reaſon of my longe cloſeneſs and painfull ſickneſs; ſo that all the favour I deſire is but the one of theſe two things. Firſt that îf I be thought to be an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender; that then I may be forthwith brought to a publick tryal, and ſuffered with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to pleade my own juſt cauſe again the Biſhops, and the Lord Keeper, and old Sir <hi>Henry Vaine</hi>'s illegall and unjuſt cenſure of me which was onely upon this ground: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I refuſed to take an illegall and unlawfull inquiſition oath, which he the Lord Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er tendred to me; which as I told him to his face in the Star-chamber is againſt the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Lawes of this land; yea againſt the petttion of right, enacted in the 3 yeer of our Soveraign King Charles; yea I told him and proved it to be againſt the Lawes of God and man, and contrary to the practiſe of the Heathens and Pagans; (as you may read in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles)</hi> yet this was the onely ground wherefore he and old Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> &amp;c. cenſured me to pay 500 pound, and to be whipt; for there was no witneſs brought againſt me face to face, onely there was read two falſe oaths made by one <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Chillington</hi> (now a Lieut. in Col. <hi>Whalyes</hi> Regiment, and one of the principal men that lately cauſed the Souldier to be ſhot to death at <hi>Pauls)</hi> whom the Biſhop hired, by giving him his liberty out of New-gate priſon for ſwearing thoſe two falſe oaths, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them other wicked ſervice of the like nature.</p>
                     <p>My Lord for my own part I deſire no mercy nor favour nor compaſſion from the greateſt of my enemies, but onely the benefit of my Soveraignes Lawes, which as I am a faithfull and loyal ſubject to my Prince and Contry, I do according to my priviledge earneſtly crave and begg not fearing by reaſon of my unſpotted Innocency the rigour of Juſtice; for my innocency is ſuch that I fear neither death nor hell, men nor Devills, hanging nor burning; for I aſſuredly know that when this my miſerable life is ended I ſhall go to my God of glory to be a poſeſſour of an immortall Crowne of glory.</p>
                     <p>In the ſecond place, if they will not let me have a ſpeedy and legal tryall, then therefore in regard my keepers are ſuch murthering, poyſoning and ſtarving fellowes, that I have juſt cauſe, in regard of their cruell bloudy threats and inveterate malice at me, to fear that they will either ſecretly by poiſon, or elſe by other wicked cruelty put me to death. I humbly and earneſtly deſire, that I may be turned over to Bridwell, Newgate, either of the Countors, or any other priſon about this City, where my friends may be ſuffered to come to me and relieve me, and look to me in my weakneſſe and great diſtreſſe; for I am neceſſitated with ſpeed to take phyſickagain to eaſe the extremity of pain which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in my head; if my Friends according to law and humanity might be ſuffered to come to look to me. And for my ſafe impriſonment, if I may be removed I will put in ſufficient ſecurity either to the L. Protector, or your ſelf for my forth-coming at all times to anſwer whatſoever the greateſt or capitalleſt of my enemies ſhall at any time object againſt me.</p>
                     <p>Now, my Lord, I have a little acquainted you with my grievous and juſt complaint, the particulars of which I offer to juſtifie and prove, it being ſuch an example of cruelty which is lawleſly and unjuſtly exerciſed upon me, which I think cannot be parallell'd in any Nation in the world, where morality and humanity are profeſſed.</p>
                     <p>Oh therefore, as you are the Noble Governour of this Renowned City, and a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of good report, make me ſome powerfull and ſpeedy help againſt the cruel Warden, whoſe lawleſs, unjuſt, and uncontrollable oppreſſions are ſo great (not only to me, but alſo to many other poor priſoners) that I think no Priſon in the world is able to parallel thoſe juſt complaints that poor diſtreſſed men are able juſtly to make againſt him; the chief of which ariſe from the Biſhop, old Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> and the Lord Keeper's bearing up the Warden in all his cruelty, for executing with tyranny and rigour their unjuſt and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97720:14"/>
Commands upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe they commit hither to be tormented in our cruel Fleet Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; which if any of the oppreſſed do but offer to ſpeak of, the Warden and his Officers do labour by lawleſſe cruelty to murther them.</p>
                     <p>Therefore it behoves you, my Lord, and my Lord Protector, now in our Soveraigns abſence [being then gone againſt the Scots] to hear the cryes of poor diſtreſſed, and too too much oppreſſed priſoners, and to eaſe them according to juſtice and right, of their intolerable burthens.</p>
                     <p>For my own part, my diſtreſſes and miſeries are ſo great, that I proteſt before the God of heaven and earth, that I had rather imbrace preſent death, then ſtill endure the piercing bitterneſſe of my oppreſſing forments: yea, I had rather chuſe to be baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the howling and doleſom wilderneſſe, and left among the Lions, Dragons, Bears and Wolves, thoſe devouring and ramping wilde beaſts, then to be as I am, in the cuſtody of the lawleſſe, murthering Biſhop and Jaylors.</p>
                     <p>O therefore, if there be any bowels of mercy and compaſſion in you, moſt Noble Lord, pity the deprorable condition of me a poor diſtreſſed innocent young man, and a Prentice of this Honourable City: And with you, my Lord, I have had occaſion to ſpeak face to face about my Maſters buſineſſe; and the laſt piece of ſervice that I did him was in your Honours Houſe. O that I were with you again, that I might with mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſollicitations ſollicite you for ſome ſpeedy redreſſe; which for our Chriſt his ſake I beſeech you let me ſhortly have, leſt the continuance in my preſent and conſtant mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, cauſe me to publiſh this in print, proclaiming it aloud to other Nations, to the publick view of all men, that ſo they may know my miſerable condition. But if I can but have any redreſſe I ſhall be ready at your Honours command to do you any ſervice that I am able; and in the interim, I ſhall with willingneſſe ſit down in peace and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. So committing you and all your brave Citizins to the keeping of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Protector, deſiring him to guide your Noble heart uprgihtly to execute Juſtice and Judgment in your great place, in theſe tormenting, oppreſſing and bloudy times; that ſo your good name for equity and juſtice may be had in perpetuity in future generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So for the preſent I humbly take my leave, and reſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt miſerable diſtreſſed, and cruelly oppreſſed poor Suppliant, JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>
                           <hi>All of this I ſubſcribe with my own bloud, which is already almoſt ſhed with cruelty: And for the ſafety of my life, ſince I was whipt, to the number of above 500 ſtripes with knotten whip-cords in leſſe then an hours ſpace, I have been forced to be let bloud four times.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And becauſe in my most cruell condition I am not ſuffered to have either pen or ink, neither of which I make uſe of in the writing of this, I am forced to ſend it very ruggedly to your Honour, and to crave pardon for thoſe literal faults that you ſhall finde in it.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                           <dateline>From the Fleet, the oppreſſingeſt and cruelleſt priſon (I think) that is in the world; the middle of this fifth Month, called <date>
                                 <hi>May,</hi> 1639.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Courteous Reader, I ſhall deſire thee to caſt thy eye ſeriouſly upon this enſuing Letter of mine and my fellow-priſoner, Mr.</hi> Richard Overton, <hi>which we wrote to the Generall the 27. of</hi> April 1649, <hi>in the behalf of Captain</hi> Savages <hi>Troopers: the Copy of which is as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:97720:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>The Copy of a Letter written to the Generall, from Lieut. Col. <hi>Jo. Lilburn</hi> and M. <hi>Rich. Overton,</hi> Arbitrary and Ari-ſtocratical priſoners in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> the 27 of <hi>April</hi> 1649, in behalf of Mr. <hi>Robert Lockier,</hi> tyrannycally ordered to be murdered by the Councel of War: M. <hi>George Aſh,</hi> M. <hi>Joſeph Hockley,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Osburn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Matth. Heyworth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> all of Captain <hi>Savage</hi> his Troop in Col. <hi>Whaley</hi>'s Regiment; who by the ſaid Councel were adjudged to caſt lots for their lives, and one of them to die.</head>
                     <head type="sub">In which it is by Law fully proved, that it is both Treaſon and Murder for any Generall or Councel of War to execute any Souldier in time of Peace, by Martiall Law.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WEe have not yet forgot your Solemn Engagement of <hi>June</hi> 5. 1647, whereby the Armies continuance as an Army was in no wiſe by the wil of the State, but by their own mutuall Agreement: and if their ſtanding were removed from one Foundation to another (as is undeniable) then with the ſame they removed from one Authority to a another; and the Ligaments and Bounds of the Firſt were all diſſolved, and gave place to the Second; and under, and from the head of their firſt Station, <hi>viz.</hi> By the will of the State, the Army derived their Government by Martiall Law; which in Judgment and Reaſon could be no longer binding then the Authority (which gave being thereto) was binding to the Army: for the denyal of the authority is an Abrogation or Nulment of all Acts, Orders, or Ordinances by that Authority, as to them: And upon this account your Excellency with the Army long proceeded upon the Conſtitution of a new Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and Government, contrary to all Martiall Law and Diſcipline, by whom onely the Army engaged to be ordered in their proſecution of the ends, to wit, Their ſeveral Rights, both as Souldiers and Commoners, for which they aſſociated; Declaring, agre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing and promiſing each other, not to Disband, Divide, or ſuffer themſelves to be Disbanded or Divided, without ſatisfaction and ſecurity, in relation to their Grievances and Deſires in behalf of themſelves and the Common-wealth, as ſhould be agreed unto by their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Agitators. And by vertue, and under colour of this Eſtabliſhment, all the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Actions by your Excellency, your Officers, and the Army have paſt: Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall to Disband, diſputing the Orders of Parliament; Impeachment and ejection of Eleven Members; your Firſt and Second March up to <hi>London;</hi> your late violent Excluſion of the major part of Members out of the Houſe, and their impriſonment without Cauſe declared, &amp;c. which can no way be juſtified from the guilt of High Treaſon, but in the accompliſhment of a righteous end, <hi>viz.</hi> The enjoyment of the benefit of our Laws and Liberties, which we hoped long ere this to have enjoyed from your hands: Yet when we conſider, and herewith compare many of your late carriages both towards the Souldiery and other Free-People; and principally your cruel exerciſe of Martiall Law, even to the Sentence and execution of Death upon ſuch of your Souldiers as ſtand for the Rights of that Engagement, &amp;c. And not only ſo, but againſt others not of the Army; we cannot but look upon your defection and Apoſtacie in ſuch dealings, as of moſt dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to all the Laws and Freedoms of the People.</p>
                     <p>And therefore, although there had never been any ſuch ſolemn Engagement by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as that of <hi>June</hi> 5. 1647. which with your Excellency in point of duty and conſcience ought not to be of the meaneſt obligation. We do proteſt againſt your exerciſe of Martiall Law, againſt any whomſoever, in time of peace, where all Courts of Juſtice are open, as the greateſt encroachment upon our Lawes and Liberties that can be acted againſt us;
<pb facs="tcp:97720:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And particularly, againſt the Tryal of the Souldiers of <hi>C. Savages</hi> Troop yeſterday, by a Court Martiall, upon the Articles of Warre, and ſentencing of two of them to death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and for no other end (as we underſtand) but for ſome diſpute about their pay: And the reaſon of this our Proteſtation, is from the Petition of Right, made in the third yeer of the late King, which declareth, <hi>That no perſon ought to be adjudged by Law Martiall, except in times of Warre; And that all Commiſſions to execute Martiall Law in time, of Peace, are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Lawes and Statutes of the Land.</hi> And it was the Parliaments complaint, That Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Law was then commanded to be executed upon Souldiers for Robbery, Mutiny, or Murder. Which Petition of Right, this preſent Parliament in their late Declarations of the 9. of Feb. and the 17. of March, 1648. commend as the moſt excellenteſt Law in England, and there promiſe to preſerve inviolably, it, and all other the Fundamentall Laws and Liberties, concerning the preſervation of the Lives, Properties, and Liberties of the people, with all things incident thereunto. And the Exerciſe, of Martiall Law in Ireland, in time of Peace, was one of the chiefeſt Articles for which the Earl of Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford loſt his head; The ſame by this preſent Parliament being judged high Treaſon. And the Parliament it ſelf, neither by Act nor Ordinance, can juſtly or warrantably deſtroy the Fundamentall Liberties and Principles of the Common Law of England: It being a <hi>maxime</hi> in Law and Reaſon both, that all ſuch Acts and Ordinances, are <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> null, and void in Law, and binds not at all, but ought to be reſiſted, and ſtood againſt to the death. And if the ſupreme Authority may not preſume to do this, much leſſe may You, or Your Officers preſume therupon; for where remedy may be had by an ordinary courſe in Law, the party grieved ſhall never have his recourſe to extraordinaries. Whence it is evident, that it is the undoubted Right of every Engliſhman (Souldier or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that he ſhould be puniſhable onely in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, according to the Lawes and Statutes of the Realme in the time of Peace, as now it is; and the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary way by Court Martiall, in no wiſe to be uſed.</p>
                     <p>Yea, the Parliaments Oracle, S. <hi>Ed. Cook.</hi> Declares in the third part of his <hi>Inſtitutes</hi> Cap. of <hi>Murther, that for a General or other Officers of an Army, in time of Peace to put any man, (although a souldier,) to death, by colour of Martiall Law, it is abſolute murther in that Generall, or Councell of War <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> Therefore erecting of Martiall Law now, when all Courts of Juſtice are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and ſtopping the free current of Law, which ſufficiently provides for the puniſhment of Souldiers as well as others, (as appears by 18. H. 6: Ch. 18, 19. &amp; 2, &amp; 3. Ed. 6. Cha. 2. 4, &amp; 5. P. &amp; M. Chap. 3. &amp; 5. Eliz. 5. &amp; 5. Jam. 21.) is an abſolute deſtroying of our Fundamentall Liberties, and the razing of the Foundation of the Common Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the which o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t of duty and Conſcience to the Rights and Freedoms of this Nation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> we value above our lives) and to leave You and all Your Councell without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, we are moved to preſent unto your Excellencie; Earneſtly preſſing, you well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what you doe, before your proceed to the taking away the lives of thoſemen by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Law; leaſt the blood of the Innocent, or the blood of War ſhed in the time of peace, (and ſo palpable ſubverſion of the Lawes and Liberties of England) bring the reward of juſt vengeance after it upon you, as it did upon the Earle of Strafford of old: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood God will not pardon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9 5. 6. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2 <hi>v.</hi> 4. 5. 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33. and what the people may do (in caſe of ſuch violent subverſion of their Rights) we ſhall leave to your Excellency to judge, and remaine</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        <signed>Your Excellencies humble Servants,
<list>
                              <item>Iohn Lilburn.</item>
                              <item>Richard Overton.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>From our Cauſeleſſe, unjuſt, and Tyranical Captivity in the Tower of London, <date>April 27. 1649.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <head>POST SCRIPT.</head>
                        <p>And that for the preſent General or his Councel to put any man to death in time of peace by Martiall Law, is not only Murder, but Treaſon, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyably proved in Capt. <hi>John Ingrams</hi> Plea, and M. <hi>William Tompſons</hi> Plea, and M. <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Croſmans</hi> Plea; all of which are printed at large in Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi>'s Book, called</p>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
